After seeing two examples that are not valid,
let's study one that is: Peterson's algorithm
(the check-order & competition approach).
In this case, we have one shared
turn variable and two flag variables,
one for each thread. The variable turn is
set to A and both flags are set to false.
In the entry section, thread
A sets its flag to true,
sets turn to B, and then waits until
turn value is B and B's flag is true.
Once A exits the critical section,
it sets its flag to false.
Let's see why this approach is valid,
and let's start with mutual exclusion.
We consider the same setup we considered before,
and we check if A can enter its critical
section while B is in its critical section.
What we can say is that, before entering
its critical section, A needs to exit the
while loop. This can happen in 2 cases:
if flagB is false or if turn is set to A.
Let's look at the first case,
let's say flagB is false.
For B to enter its critical section, it needs
to set flagB to true (first instruction of
the entry section). Since we are considering
the case in which A sees flagB set to false,
it means in this case B would set flagB to
true after A sees flagB being false (we use
an arrow connecting event X to event
Y to denote that X happened before Y).
After setting its flag to
true, B sets turn to idA.
Then B will enter the while loop.
Will B exit it? Not until it sees flagA
being false, but that will only happen
after A exits its critical section, which means
we cannot find a counterexample in this case.
We are left with the second case,
let's say A sees the turn value is idA.
Let's resume our previous example.
A sets flagA to true, then A sets
turn to idB, and finally, A sees turn is
equal to idA and thus exits the while loop.
Notice in this case the value
of turn was set to B by A
in the second instruction of the entry
section, but then B must have set it to
A for A to read its id during the execution
of the third instruction of the entry set.
After setting turn to idA B enters its while
loop. Can it exit it and enter its critical
section before A? No, because turn is set to
idA and flagA will remain true until A exits
its critical section. So, also in this
case, we cannot find a counter-example.
As for previous algorithms, you can switch A and B
and show B cannot enter its critical
section while A is running its own.
Now that we know mutual execution
is guaranteed, let's check progress.
Can it happen that one thread wants
to enter its critical section,
but it has to wait for unbounded time while the
other thread is not in its critical section?
Can A want to enter its critical
section and be waiting for B even
though B is not in its critical section?
It is easy to show this is not possible: if A is
waiting, then B can enter its critical section
because flagB is true and turn value is idB.
But if B is in its reminder section, then flagB
is false, which means A can enter its section.
Similarly, if B is waiting,
then A can enter its critical
section because flagA is true and
turn value is idA or B can enter
its own because A set flagA to false
before entering its reminder section
We are now left with fairness. In this case,
we are going to look into bounded waiting.
Is it possible for one thread, let's say
B, to wait to enter its critical section
while A manages to enter its critical
section an unbounded number of times?
Let's try to find an example of this happening.
In this case, A is running its
critical section and B is waiting.
What we are trying to find is an execution in
which A enters again its critical section while
B still waits. If this can happen once, then
it can happen an unbounded number of times.
After exiting its critical
section, A sets flagA to false.
A runs its reminder section and then starts
the loop again by setting flagA to true.
Then, A sets turn to idB
and enters the while loop.
If B is waiting in its loop, then flagB is true.
The value of turn is idB (because A just set it).
Then, we can conclude A cannot
exit the loop until B is done
with its critical section.
Hence, this cannot happen.
As before, swap A with B, and
the same reasoning applies.
So, after all this, we can conclude
that Peterson's algorithm is valid!
Before moving to the next part of the lecture,
please have a look at these links about
counterexamples and proofs by way of contradiction
if you are not familiar with these concepts.